A Guide to the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation records FA1501
Rockefeller Archive Center
William and Flora Hewlett Foundation records
1966-2014
Rockefeller Archive Center
William & Flora Hewlett Foundation
FA1501
32.42 Cubic Feet 66 containers
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation in 2019.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Arrangement
The William and Flora Hewlett Foundation records are arranged as received, represented by following series:
Series 1: President's Office, 1967-2014
Series 2: Photographs, 1980-2005
Series 3: Published Material, 1966-2016
Series 4: Conflict Resolution Program, 1984-2004
Series 5: Oral History Project, 1995-2004
Series 6: Annual Reports, 1966-2008
Series 7: Board of Directors Meeting Dockets, 2000-2014
Series 8: Grant Products, 1999-2012
Series 9: San Diego School Reform, 1998-2004
Series 10: Bay Area School Reform Collaborative (BASRC), 1994-2004
Series 11: San Francisco Bay Area Performance Space, 1986-2012
Series 12: Audio Visual Material, 1998-2012
Series 13: Oversize Material, 2005-2012
Biographical / Historical
William (Bill) Hewlett was a founding partner of the Hewlett-Packard Company, which was started in 1939. Longtime supporters of environmental and social-issue non-profit groups as well as the performing arts, he and his wife, Flora, formed the Hewlett Foundation on November 27, 1966. The Foundation began with only three trustees: Bill and Flora Hewlett along with their son, Walter. In the early days, it was very much a small family foundation, with many of the giving considerations reflecting the Hewletts' personal philanthropic giving and decisions being made during meetings in the family living room.
The Hewlett Foundation hired its first executive director, John May, in 1974. May had formerly been the director of the San Francisco Foundation in which Bill Hewlett had long been involved. Under May's leadership the Foundation formalized the application review procedure and expanded its board leadership outside of the Hewlett family. He also increased the hiring of a variety of consultants to assist the Foundation in its different program areas. One of these consultants, Ted Lobman, became the Foundation's first full-time program officer, with a focus on education. One of the key tenets, both of the Hewlett-Packard Company and the Hewlett Foundation, was a management style that became known as the "HP Way." This management style emphasized an informal work environment in which the working groups were given independence and latitude in decision making as well as a focus on the interpersonal connections, stressing that coworkers should care for one another and their communities. Though there was no formal system of programs, under the leadership of Bill and Flora Hewlett, the Foundation focused on five main issues: healthcare, environment, population, education, and quality of life in the San Francisco Bay Area.
Flora Hewlett died in 1977 and upon her death, almost the entirety of her estate went to the Foundation, increasing its endowment exponentially. At the same time, Bill Hewlett stepped away from day-to-day management at Hewlett-Packard and stepped into the role of board chair at the Foundation while Roger Heyns took over the role of president of the Foundation from John May. During his tenure at the Foundation, he reshaped it from the small family foundation that made decisions based on organizations known to the president and board members to a large foundation that used a formal procedure and professional staff to seek out programs that were most deserving in the targeted areas that the Foundation chose to support. Under Heyns the Foundation ended their program support for healthcare (he felt the field was too amorphous and already being well funded by other foundations) and expanded into funding in the area of conflict resolution and began a program on US-Mexico relations.
In 1993, David Gardner took over as president of the Foundation upon Roger Heyns' retirement. As HP stock increased in price, Gardner developed an investment strategy that proved highly successful for the Foundation and led to rapid growth in the Foundation's assets. Under Gardner's leadership, term limits by program staff were also formalized. The Foundation had long encouraged term limits for the Foundation to increase new ideas among staff while trying to avoid having program officers be too overly connected to grantees. This process was formalized under Gardner, limiting program officer's terms to six years (with a possible three years extension given by the board). This was extended to eight years in 2005.
Paul Brest took over leadership in the Foundation in 2000, and the following year Bill Hewlett passed away. Upon Hewlett's death, the assets of the Foundation almost tripled, making it the fifth largest private foundation in the country. Paul Brest remained as Foundation president until 2012. Under his leadership the Foundation continued its existing grant making while expanding its initiatives to include work in the areas of climate change and the use of open education resources. The Foundation also merged its programs on global development and population (approximately 2008) and moved into new headquarters in Menlo Park, California.
Larry Kramer, a former dean at Stanford Law School, took over as Foundation president in 2012. Under his leadership, the Foundation has added to new time-bound initiatives examining the challenges of cybersecurity and addressing the problem of the increasing polarization in politics and its role on the effectiveness of the U.S. government.
Scope and Contents
The William and Flora Hewlett Foundation records documents the foundation's early history and programs. The majority of the material is biographical in nature, with only a small amount of grant-related records which can be found in the Grant Products series.
Teachers--Training of; Educational evaluation -- California -- San Diego (Calif.); English language -- Study and teaching; Equality -- Education -- United States; Education -- Standards; Economic development; Economic policy; Global Development; United States -- Relations -- Latin America; Performing arts; Population; San Diego (Calif.)
- President's Office, 1967-2014; 1; 1.52 Cubic Feet 4 letter document boxes
  - Annual Report, 1967-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Spreadsheets on grants made, sorted by program and by recipient.
  - President's Statements, 1976-1996 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    President's Statements, 1976-1999 (Reprinted May 1999). This is a bound compilation of all the "President's Statements" printed as an introduction to each Hewlett Foundation Annual Report. Two copies.
  - Planning - Strategic Planning Memos to David P. Gardner, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    From a "Three Memos" exercise, to David Gardner from the program directors (Performing Arts, Education, Family and Community Development, U.S. - Latin American Relations, Conflict Resolution, Environment, and Population). First written in June/July 1997 and then revised in January/February 1998.
  - Planning - Request for Planning Information, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Memo from Paul Brest to staff, July 26, 1999.
  - Planning - Education, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Review of K-12 Programs: Background Materials, Social Policy Research Associates
    Education Program Objectives, Assessment, and Forward Planning Memo to Paul Brest from Ray Bacchetti and Ida Oberman, October 7, 1999
    Brief Thoughts on Directions for the Foundation's K-12 Education Program, memo to Ray Bacchetti, Ida Oberman, and David L. Kripp, February 16, 2000
    Toward an Education Agenda for the Hewlett Foundation, David L. Kripp, February 2000
    Toward a Higher Education Agenda for Foundations, David l. Kripp, January 2000
    The Future of the Hewlett Foundation Education Program, Ida Oberman to David Krip, Paul Brest, Ray Bacchetti Michael Smith, Education Program: Notes for Board Meeting (February 11, 2001)
  - Planning - United States-Latin America Relations, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    U.S.-Latin American Relations Program overview
    U.S.-Latin American Relations Program Strategic Planning Ideas David Lorey
    Report to the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation on the Program on U.S.-Latin American Relations, John H. Coatsworth, Harvard University, September 2000.
    Current Grants; Current Collaborative Grants, no date
    Email from David Lorey to Paul Brest, Subject: Memo of Jan. 19 (Review and Strategic Planning)
    Memo to Board of Directors from Paul Brest Strategic Planning for U.S. Latin American Relations Program, October 7, 2000.
  - Planning - Population Program, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Population Program Summary
    2000 Budget Planning Memorandum, Population Program
    Population Program Review
  - Planning - Performing Arts, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Response to July 26, 1999 Memo, Melanie Beene to Paul Brest
    Performing Arts Program
    Outline of January 2000 meeting with Paul Brest and Susan Bell
    Planning outline and timeline, Melanie Beene to Paul Brest and Susan Bell, January 26, 2000
  - Planning - Family and Community Development, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Program Summary
    Response to July 26 Memo, Alvertha Penny to Paul Brest, October 8, 1999
    Background Paper on a Proposed Asset Accumulation Funding Category and an Update on Local and National IDA Programs, Alvertha Penny to Paul Brest, November 29, 1999
    Comparison of Funders, Alvertha Penny to Paul Brest, December 22, 1999
    Proposed Consultants for Strategic Planning Process, Alvertha Penny and Renu Karir to Paul Brest, January 19, 2000
    Strategic Planning Process Experts, Thoughtful Observers and Critics (Revised) List, Alvertha Penny to Paul Brest and Susan Bell, February 4, 2000
    Recommendations for Consultant: Cluster Evaluation of Employment Development Grantees, Alvertha Penny to Paul Brest, February 14, 2000.
    Strategic Planning Process Experts, Thoughtful Observers and Critics (Revised) List, Alvertha Penny to Paul Brest and Susan Bell, February 22, 2000
    Meeting Notes: Family and Community Development Neighborhood Revitalization Strategic Planning Advisory Meeting, Tuesday, June 13, 2000
    Documents from Disadvantage Children and Youth Strategic Planning Advisory Meeting, New York, October 10-11, 2000
    Documents from Disadvantaged Children and Youth Strategic Planning Advisory Meeting, Palo Alto, October 19-20, 2000
  - Planning - Program Officer Meeting, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Problem Solving based on a draft of a work in progress by Paul Brest and Linda Hamilton-Krieger
    Exhibits 1-8: Draft budget memoranda from the eight programs, 1999-2000
  - Presidential Transition, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Organization Charts
    Letter from Paul Brest to Walter Hewlett re: board meeting and proposed new administration positions (July 12, 1999)
    Miscellaneous correspondence about transition, new hires, people to meet, Annenberg and Bay Area School Reform Collaborative
  - Neighborhood Improvement Initiative, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
    Neighborhood Improvement Initiative (1999)
    One East Palo Alto Neighborhood Improvement Initiative Community Plan. The Community of Palo Alto with assistance from the Peninsula Community Foundation, et. al. June 26, 2000.
    Revised Resource List Prepared for NII Planning Groups: Programs Serving East Palo Alto.
    Haas Center for Public Service at Stanford University. April 25, 2000.
    Community Profile: East Palo Alto. Haas Center for Public Service, Stanford University. October 2002.
  - Social Policy Research, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Evaluation of K-12 Education Grantmaking at the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation, Social Policy Research (March 27, 2000)
  - Foundation Initiatives for Children, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Public/Private Ventures, Foundation Initiatives for Children, Youth and Families: A View of the Landscape (October 2002)
  - Strategic Plans, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Susan Bell, Strategic Plans for 2003.
  - President's Memos, 2000-2008 (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
  - President's Memos, 2009-2014 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted - Open in 2025.
  - Between Meetings Newsletter, 2003-2005 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Board Minute Notes, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Nancy Strausser, Assistant to the President, handwritten notes in advance of the Board meeting minutes.
  - Program Memoranda, 2006-2009 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Program Associate Grantmaking Manual, 2009 September 4 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - New Building 2121 Sand Hill Road, 1998-2001 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Memo to staff "The Buck Estate" (August 7, 1998)
    Contact sheet photographs of site preparation "If You Build it They Will Come" (2001)
    "New Office Plans for Hewlett Foundation" Photocopy of clipping.
  - Newsletters, 2004-2006 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Financial Statements, 2002-2010 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Form 990-PF, 2002-2012 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Carnegie Medal of Philanthropy, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Background Materials, 1997-1999 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    Materials compiled to help with the oral history interviews.
    Roger W. Heyns, Concept Paper: Public Policy Institute of California (1997)
    Development Studies Center
    Bay Area School Reform Collaborative: Annual Report (Fall 1999)
  - John May, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    Reprints of materials written by the Foundation's first president.
  - Stanford Hewlett Challenge, 2007-2011 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    Celebrating Transformative Philanthropy: The 10th Anniversary of the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation Gift to Stanford University (2011)
  - William R. Hewlett, 1976-2001 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    William R. Hewlett to Roger W. Heyns (June 25, 1976); handwritten notes on Heyn's letter sent July 12, 1976
    William R. Hewlett to Arjay Miller (August 6, 1971)
    Arjay Miller, Notes for Eulogy of Bill Hewlett (January 20, 2001)
    Sheet music, "Goodbyes Unnecessary-Forever Connected by Music
  - William R. Hewlett Memorial Service, 2001 January 20 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - William R. Hewlett National Academy of Sciences Biographical Memoir, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - William R. Hewlett Newspaper Clippings, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    "Hewlett Packard Co Founder Dies" Oregonian (January 13, 2001), Section E Page 1
    "High Tech Pioneer Hewlett Dies" San Francisco Chronicle (January 13, 2001) Section 1 Page 1
  - Newspaper Clippings, 2001-2013 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Newspaper Clippings - Green Building, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    'Green' Buildings: Energy Efficiency, "Thoughtful Design Pay Off," San Jose Mercury News, March 30, 2004, E1.
- Photographs, 1980-2005; 2; 1.14 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Oral History Photos, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    Photos collected by Gabrielle Morris in 1999 to include in the oral histories she worked on. Mix of originals and paper prints.
  - Hewlett Foundation Building, undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
    Photographs of HF Building prior to occupation. Envelope has names of Marvin Wax and Jo Conover.
  - World Neighbors Presentation, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Bill Hewlett Family, 1980 September (Box 4, Folder 43)
    Formal portrait of whole family, September 1980.
  - Peter Hewlett, 1990 February (Box 4, Folder 44)
    Formal portraits of Peter Hewlett and his wife.
  - Neighborhood Improvement Initiative Parade, East Palo Alto, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - LBJ Presidential Library Photos, undated (Box 5)
    CD of 2 photos of Bill Hewlett meeting President Johnson
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
  - Jim Hewlett, 1991 December (Box 5, Folder 46)
    Formal sitting portraits of Jim Hewlett taken by Carole de Gery.
  - Neighborhood Improvement Initiative Meeting, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 47-50)
  - Hewlett Foundation Picnic, 1992 April (Box 6, Folder 51)
    San Felipe Ranch (April 1992). Includes photos of Bill Hewlett and Roger Heyns.
  - Hewlett Foundation Dinner, undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
    Before 2001, includes photos of Bill Hewlett, Roger Heyns, and David Gardner.
  - Population Program - Africa Trip, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 53)
- Published Material, 1966-2016; 3; 1.14 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes
  - History of the Performing Arts Program by Laurie MacDougall, 1966-2016 (Box 6, Folder 54-55)
  - A Practical Guide to Outcome-Focused Philanthropy, 2016 November (Box 6, Folder 56-57)
  - The Flora Family Foundation: The Early Years, 1998-2003 by Herant Katchadourian, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - Personnel Policies Handbook, 1999 June (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - No Reason to Wait: The Benefits of Greenhouse Gas Reduction in Sao Paulo and California, 2005 December (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - No Reason to Wait: The Benefits of Greenhouse Gas Reduction in Sao Paulo and California CD, 2005 December (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Improving the Practice of Philanthropy: An Evaluation of the Hewlett Foundation's Knowledge Creation and Dissemination Strategy, 2013 September 25 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Open Educational Resource Initiative, undated (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Taking Action on Climate Change, undated (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - The Hewlett Foundation in Mexico: A Growing Partnership, undated (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Solving Problems for the Common Good, undated (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - The Population Program: Solving Problems for the Common Good, undated (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - The Hewlett Foundation Building: Environmental Values at Work, undated (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Environmental Conflict Resolution: Strategies for Environmental Grantmakers, undated (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Collaborative Governance: A Guide for Grantmakers, undated (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Community Development: A Guide for Grantmakers on Fostering Better Outcomes through Good Process, undated (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - The Flora Family Foundation - Annual Reports, 1999-2012 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Annual Brochures, 1979-2002 (Box 8, Folder 72-73)
  - The Founding of the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation: A History Prepared on the Occasion of its 50th Anniversary, 2016 September 1 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - 50 Years of Philanthropy DVD, 2016 (Box 8)
- Conflict Resolution Program, 1984-2004; 4; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
  - Budget Memoranda, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Transmittal Letter, undated (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Annual Meeting, 1995-1998 (Box 8, Folder 77-79)
  - Annual Meeting, 2000-2004 (Box 9, Folder 80-86)
- Oral History Project, 1995-2004; 5; 1.52 Cubic Feet 4 letter document boxes
  A thirty-year history project, 1966-1999. Conducted by Gabrielle Morris.
  - Transcripts, 1999-2001; 1
    - Series Introduction: The Past is Prologue - Interviewee List and Partial Chronology, 2001 September (Box 10, Folder 87)
    - Ray Bacchetti: Invigorating Hewlett Education Programs, 1993-1999, 1999 November (Box 10, Folder 88)
    - Dyke Brown, Education Consultant, 1978-1993: Teaching Ethics and Values, 1999 October (Box 10, Folder 89)
    - Hugh Burroughs: New Dimensions in Regional Grantmaking, 1977-1988, 1999 August (Box 10, Folder 90)
    - Alice DePalma Davis: John May and the Hewlett Foundation, 1975-1977, 1999 August (Box 10, Folder 91)
    - Robert Erburu: Future Challenges and Opportunities, a Trustee's View, 1999 October (Box 10, Folder 92)
    - James C. Gaither: A Trustee's View on Leadership Responsibilities, 1999 June (Box 10, Folder 93)
    - David P. Gardner: Experiences as President of the Foundation, 1993-1999, 1999 November (Box 10, Folder 94)
    - Eleanor Hewlett Gimon: Trustees' Growing Workload and New Responsibilities, 2000 January (Box 10, Folder 95)
    - Patricia Gump: The Conflict Resolution Program and Life at the Foundation, 1979-1999, 1999 November (Box 11, Folder 96)
    - James Hewlett: One-on-One Philanthropy, 1999 September (Box 11, Folder 97)
    - Walter B. Hewlett: Becoming Chairman of the Board, 1966-1995, 1998-1999 (Box 11, Folder 98)
    - William A. Hewlett: Family Values in the Hewlett Foundation, 1972-1980, 1999 September (Box 11, Folder 99)
    - Roger W. Heyns: Collected Thoughts on Grantmaking and the Hewlett Foundation, 1986-1989 (Box 11, Folder 100)
    - Mary Jaffe: The Next Generations - Preparing for Change, 1999 November (Box 11, Folder 101)
    - Herant Katchadourian: On Trusteeship and Friendship, 1989-1999, 1999 June (Box 11, Folder 102)
    - Theodore Lobman: At the Fulcrum of Educational Change, 1977-1985, 1999 August (Box 11, Folder 103)
    - Arjay Miller: Hewlett Foundation Trusteeship, 1978-1995, 1999 June (Box 12, Folder 104)
    - Anne Firth Murray: Developments in Environment and Population Programs, 1978-1987, 1999 September (Box 12, Folder 105)
    - William Nichols: Responsibilities and Observations of the Treasurer, 1985-1999, 1999 November (Box 12, Folder 106)
    - Marianne Pallotti: Vice President and Corporate Secretary, 1977-1999, 1999 January (Box 12, Folder 107)
    - Alvertha Bratton Penny: Community Development Grants, 1994-1999: Investment in Leadership, 1999 November (Box 12, Folder 108)
    - B. Stephen Toben: Refining and Expanding Grantmaking, 1991-1999: the Conflict Resolution Program, 1999 November (Box 12, Folder 109)
  - Background Materials, 1995-2004; 2
    - Notes on Working Copies, 2004 (Box 12, Folder 110)
    - Correspondence, 2000-2003 (Box 12, Folder 111)
    - Series List, undated (Box 12, Folder 112)
    - Legal Agreements on Use, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 113)
    - Correspondence - Bacchetti, 1999-2000 (Box 13, Folder 114)
    - Correspondence - Brown, 1999-2000 (Box 13, Folder 115)
    - Correspondence - Burroughs, 1999-2000 (Box 13, Folder 116)
    - Correspondence - Davis, 1999-2000 (Box 13, Folder 117)
    - Correspondence - Erburu, 1999-2001 (Box 13, Folder 118)
    - Correspondence - Gaither, 1999-2001 (Box 13, Folder 119)
    - Correspondence - Gardner, 1998-2000 (Box 13, Folder 120)
    - Correspondence - Gimon (Hewlett), 1999-2002 (Box 13, Folder 121)
    - Correspondence - Gump, 1999-2000 (Box 13, Folder 122)
    - Correspondence - Hewlett, James, 1999-2001 (Box 13, Folder 123)
    - Correspondence - Hewlett, Walter, 1998-2001 (Box 13, Folder 124)
    - Correspondence - Hewlett, William, 1999-2001 (Box 13, Folder 125)
    - Correspondence - Jaffe, 1999-2001 (Box 13, Folder 126)
    - Correspondence - Katchadourian, 1999-2001 (Box 13, Folder 127)
    - Correspondence - Lobman, 1999-2000 (Box 13, Folder 128)
    - Correspondence - Miller, 1999-2000 (Box 13, Folder 129)
    - Correspondence - Murray, 1999-2000 (Box 13, Folder 130)
    - Correspondence - Nichols, 1999-2000 (Box 13, Folder 131)
    - Correspondence - Pallotti, 1999-2000 (Box 13, Folder 132)
    - Correspondence - Penny, 1999-2000 (Box 13, Folder 133)